Guide to the Semans family papers, 1878-2008 and undated RL.01167
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Semans family papers
1878-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Semans family
RL.01167
76.2 Linear Feet
Collection consists of correspondence, financial papers, legal papers, writings and speeches, scrapbooks, photographs, films, audio tapes, and other materials reflecting the philanthropic, financial, cultural and social activities of the Semans family and other wealthy families in North Carolina and New York. A major focus is the interrelationship of the Semans family with the Biddle, Duke, and Trent families. Additionally, the papers document the roles of Mary Duke Biddle, James H. Semans and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans have taken in the development and support of arts and educational programs throughout North Carolina. To a lesser degree, the papers reflect women in politics and childcare issues during the early 20th century.
Access Restrictions
Access to the materials will be consistent with the 1991 agreement between the Library, James H. Semans and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans. Access to any correspondence, legal papers, and financial papers is restricted and will be permitted only with prior written permission. Written permission should be sought from the chairperson of the board of the Mary Duke Biddle Foundation. This restriction shall be in place until January 1, 2027 and after that date all materials shall be considered open for research and will not require any prior permissions.
Provenance
The Semans Family Papers were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by James Hustead and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans beginning in 1969 through 2017. The collection includes the papers of Mary Duke Biddle and Elizabeth Lucina Gotham. Funds from The Duke Endowment supported the processing of the collection.
Biographical Note
Mary Duke Biddle
1887, Nov. 16 Born, Durham, N.C.
1907 A.B., Trinity College, Durham, N.C.
ca. 1914 Presented at the Court of St. James, London, England
1915, June 16 Married Anthony J. Drexel Biddle (divorced 1931)
1931 Presented Duke Homestead to Duke University
1936 Supported expansion of the Sarah P. Duke Gardens, Duke University
1946 Supported expansion of the Duke University Library, including its Rare Book Room
1956 Established Mary Duke Biddle Foundation
1960, June 1 Died, Durham, N.C.
James H. Semans
1910, May 30 Born, Uniontown, Pa.
1928 Graduated, Lawrenceville School, Lawrenceville, N.J.
1932 A.B., Princeton University
1936 M.D., Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
1936-1943 Medical resident: Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore, Md.; St. Mary's Hospital, Pierre, S.D.; Ancker Hospital, St. Paul, Minn.
1944-1946 U.S. Army, various stateside military base hospitals
1947-1953 Private practice in urology, Atlanta, Ga.
1953, Oct. 17 Married Mary Duke Biddle Trent
1953-1980 Duke University Medical Center, (Assoc. Professor of Urology 1953-1960, Professor 1960-1980, Emeritus 1980- )
1954-1963 Duke University Medical Center, Rehabilitation Program
1964-1981 North Carolina School of the Arts, Board of Trustees, Chairman (Honorary Trustee 1981- )
1964- North Carolina School of the Arts Foundation, Inc., ex-officio Chairman
Dr. Semans's extensive commitment to the areas of vocational and physical rehabilitation began while he was in the Army and developed into an interest in local, state, and national programs. He served on the boards of the United Medical Research Foundation of North Carolina (1956); the National Rehabilitation Association, N.C. Chapter (1955-1958) [Life Member of the national organization]; the National Paraplegia Foundation (1955-1972); the Board of Directors of Operation Breakthrough [a Durham vocational rehabilitation program] (1965-1967); and the Governor's Executive Committee on Employment of the Handicapped (1965-1971). He was named Mary Switzer Scholar at New York University in 1984. He lectured worldwide on the subject of urology.
The primary institutional focus of Dr. Semans's support of the arts is the North Carolina School of the Arts in Winston-Salem, N.C., and activities extending from that commitment, including the promotion of artists of all types. His position with the school involves him in many other arts-related activities including the North Carolina Arts Council (1982?). Dr. Semans was a trustee of Louisburg and Warren Wilson colleges and is on the Board of Trustees of the Mary Duke Biddle Foundation (1960-).
Many organizations have recognized Dr. Semans's achievements with awards. These include the National Conference of Christians and Jews National Brotherhood Award (1969); the North Carolina Award for Significant Contributions to the Arts (1972); and the North Carolina Society Award (1986). Each of these awards was received jointly with Mary D.B.T. Semans.
Biographical note
Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans
1920, Feb. 21 Born, New York City, N.Y.
1938, June 24 Married Josiah Charles Trent (died Dec. 1948)
1939 A.B., Duke University (diploma received 1951)
1951-1955 Durham City Council member
1953, Oct. 17 Married James H. Semans
1960- The Duke Endowment (Trustee 1960-1970, Vice-Chairman 1970-1981, Chairman 1982- )
1960- Mary Duke Biddle Foundation (Chairman 1960-1983)
1961-1981 Duke University Board of Trustees (Emeritus 1981- )
1981-1985 (?) North Carolina School of the Arts, Board of Trustees
Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans lived her early years in Tarrytown and New York City, N.Y. She attended the Hewitt School in New York. She moved to Durham, N.C., in 1934. After marrying physician Josiah Charles Trent, she moved between Michigan and Durham while Dr. Trent participated in several hospital residency programs. They returned to Durham around 1947 when Dr. Trent established the Department of Thoracic Surgery at Duke University Hospital.
Mary D.B.T. Semans is active in administrative development and academic and artistic programs of Duke University and is on the Board of The Duke Endowment. Since the 1950s Mrs. Semans served on boards of numerous civic, academic, and social welfare organizations in Durham and the state of North Carolina. She was Durham Mayor Pro-Tem (1953-1955) and President of Durham Homes, Inc. (1968). She served on the North Carolina Museum of Art Committee (1961-1983); the Executive Mansion Fine Arts Committee [Chairman] (1965-); and the North Carolina Symphony Board of Trustees (1972-1983).
In the area of vocational rehabilitation, Mrs. Semans served on the National Advisory Council on Vocational Rehabilitation (1961-1965); the National Citizens Advisory Commission on Vocational Rehabilitation (1966) [appointed by President Johnson]; the Governor's Study Committee on Vocational Rehabilitation [Chairman] (1967-1969); and the Special National Subcommittee on Vocational Rehabilitation (1968).
She was a trustee of several colleges and universities including Louisburg (1959-1965), Shaw (1962-1974), Converse (1964-1967), and Davidson, and a member of various boards of visitors and committees of other educational institutions, including Wake Forest University. She received honorary degrees from universities and colleges including North Carolina Central (1963), Elon (1965), Campbell (1971), University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (1977), Davidson (1980), Pfeiffer (1984), and North Carolina Wesleyan (1982).
Many organizations have recognized Mrs. Semans's achievements with awards. These include the National Conference of Christians and Jews National Brotherhood Award (1969); the North Carolina Award for Significant Contributions to the Arts (1972); and the North Carolina Society Award (1986). These awards were received jointly with James H. Semans. She also received the North Carolina Citizens for Business and Industry Citation for Distinguished Public Service (1984) and the North Carolina Distinguished Service Award for Women (1985). Duke University presented her the Distinguished Alumni Award (1986) and the University Medal for Meritorious Service (1986).
Biographical note
Elizabeth Lucina Gotham
1887 Born, Pierpoint, N.Y.
ca. 1912 Graduated as nurse from St. Margaret's Baby Hospital, Albany, N.Y.
ca. 1917-1920 Baby nurse for families and in a hospital [St. Christopher's?], Brooklyn, N.Y.
1920, Oct. 25 Employed by Biddle family as baby nurse for Mary Duke Biddle (Trent Semans), New York, N.Y.
1968 Died, Durham, N.C.
Collection Overview
The papers of the Semans family span the years 1878 to 2008. The collection consists of four large sub-collections: the Mary Duke Biddle Family Papers, the James H. Semans Family Papers, the James H. and Mary D.B.T. Semans Family Papers, and the Elizabeth Lucina Gotham Family Papers. There are also series for films, oversize materials, and later additions.
Through files of correspondence, financial papers, legal papers, writings and speeches, scrapbooks, photographs, films, audio tapes, and other materialsThe collection reflects the philanthropic, financial, cultural, and social activities of the Semans family. Major areas of focus are the personal and social relationships of the Semans family with the Biddle, Duke, and Trent, and other wealthy families from North Carolina, New York, and elsewhere. Additionally, the papers document the roles Mary Duke Biddle, James H. Semans, and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans have taken in the development and support of arts and educational programs throughout North Carolina. To a lesser degree, the papers reflect on women in politics and childcare during the early twentieth century.
Individuals represented include Mary Duke Biddle (daughter of Benjamin Duke), Anthony Joseph Drexel Biddle, Nicholas Benjamin Duke Biddle, Angier Biddle Duke, Angier Buchanan Duke, Benjamin Newton Duke, Sarah Pearson Angier Duke, Elizabeth Lucina Gotham, and Josiah Charles Trent as well as other members of the Duke, Biddle, Trent, and Semans families. Political, arts, and educational leaders are also represented.
Subject areas represented include: families in the late 19th and 20th centuries; the arts in North Carolina and other cities; charities, particularly in North Carolina; childcare and women in nursing; The Duke Endowment; Duke University and other universities and colleges; the North Carolina School of the Arts; education; genealogy of the four families; personal finances; philanthropy; the history of Durham, NC, and its politics and social life; vocational rehabilitation; and the Methodist church, particularly in NC.
The 25 16mm film reels in the collection are chiefly children's cartoons from the 1930s-1940s, but there are also wartime newsreels and a few films for adults, some as early as 1916-1917, and some travel film. Audio tapes consist chiefly of personal family recordings, a set of memoirs dictated onto cassettes in 1977 by Mary D.B.T. Semans, and music performances.
Some portions of the collection are restricted or closed to use; please consult this collection guide for details before coming to use these materials.
For additional collections of Duke family papers, see the Washington Duke Papers, the Benjamin Newton Duke Papers, and the James B. Duke Papers. For further information on the contributions of the Duke family to Duke University, contact the Duke University Archives.
Methodist Church -- North Carolina; Arts -- North Carolina; Charities -- North Carolina; Childcare -- 20th century; Education -- North Carolina; Families -- United States -- 19th century; Families -- United States -- 20th century; Millionaires -- North Carolina; Philanthropists -- North Carolina; Social history -- 19th century; Social history -- 20th century; Universities and colleges -- North Carolina; Women in public life -- North Carolina; Women in politics -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Autochromes (photographs); Black-and-white film; Black-and-white photographs; Carbon prints; Color photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Phonograph records; Photograph albums; Scrapbooks; Home movies; Audiovisual materials; Duke Endowment; Duke family; Duke University; Duke, Angier Buchanan, 1884-1923; Gotham, Elizabeth Lucina, 1887-1968; North Carolina School of the Arts; Semans family; Semans, James H.; Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent; Trent family; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995; Duke, Sarah Pearson Angier, 1856-1936; Biddle, Nicholas Benjamin Duke, 1921-; Biddle, Mary Duke, 1887-1960; Biddle, Anthony Joseph Drexel, 1896-1961; Biddle family; Duke, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Newton); Trent, Josiah C. (Josiah Charles), 1914-1948
- Mary Duke Biddle Family Papers, 1894-1960
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to any correspondence, legal papers, and financial papers is restricted and will be permitted only with prior written permission. Please see the collection-level access restrictions for more information.
  Scope and Contents
  The Mary Duke Biddle Family Papers span the years 1894 to 1960, although the bulk of the material dates from the 1920s to the 1930s. They consist of correspondence, legal papers, scrapbooks, photographs, address books, expense accounts, wedding memorabilia, baby books, and other materials documenting Mrs. Biddle's personal and family life, and social, cultural, and philanthropic activities.
  The Correspondence series consists primarily of correspondence to and from Mary Duke Biddle, but also includes correspondence to and from Anthony J. Drexel Biddle, Benjamin N. Duke, Sarah P. Duke, Angier Buchanan Duke, Mary D.B.T. Semans and Nicholas Benjamin Duke Biddle, and Duke University officers, board members, and faculty. There is also a significant amount of correspondence from Duke family business managers that relates to Mrs. Biddle's private finances and correspondence from Mrs. Biddle to Duke University wherein she continued the Duke family tradition of giving to Duke University. Some legal papers relating to financial transactions and purchases are interspersed with correspondence. There are many condolences addressed to Mrs. Biddle on the deaths of her brother, father, and mother as well as other materials relating to the death and funeral of B.N. Duke. Additional materials related to the death of B.N. Duke are in the collection of Benjamin Newton Duke Papers, also held in the Rubenstein Library.
  The Scrapbooks Series contains newspaper society page clippings about the Duke and Biddle families and Duke University. Some scrapbooks contain correspondence to and from Benjamin N. Duke, primarily related to Duke University. Mrs. Biddle's interest in the performing arts is reflected in scrapbooks which contain primarily photomechanical pictures of opera and theater celebrities.
  Four autochrome portraits of Mrs. Biddle and Sarah P. Duke are in the Pictures Series. The autochromes, a rare early color photographic process, are displayed in diascope cases and date from about 1910. Other photographs, including one carbon print from the mid 1920s, are of Mrs. Biddle and her family and friends at Biddle's Durham residence "Pinecrest" in the 1950s. Numerous portraits of Mary Duke Biddle are also found in the Pictures Series of the James H. and Mary D.B.T. Semans Family Papers.
  Some larger photographs and other materials are in the Oversize Materials series found at the end of the Semans Family papers.
  - Correspondence Series
    - 1894-1919 (Box 1)
    - 1920-1960,undated, 16 folders (Box 1)
    - Condolences: (Box 2)
      - Angier Buchanan Duke
        - 1923, Sept.-Oct.,undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Telegrams, 1923, Sept. (Box 2)
      - Benjamin Newton Duke
        - 1929, Jan.-June (Box 2)
        - 1929,Funeral (Box 2)
      - Sarah P. Duke
        - 1936, Sept.-Nov.,undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Telegrams, 1936, Sept. (Box 2)
  - Legal Papers Series
    - Wills: (Box 2)
      - Biddle, Mary Duke, 1960 (Box 2)
      - Duke, Benjamin N., 1926and Duke, Sarah P., 1936 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks Series
    - Bridal book, 1915 (Box 3)
    - Opera/Theater Personalities, 1900-1920 (Box 3)
    - Baby book ( Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans), 1920 (Box 3)
    - Baby book ( Nicholas Benjamin Duke Biddle), 1921 (Box 4)
    - Family, 1928-1932 (Box 4)
  - Pictures Series
    Fragile, handle with care!
    The autochromes are on glass and are very fragile. Please handle with care. Digital surrogates are available and are preferred for research access.
    - Duke, Sarah P. (autochrome), circa 1910 (Box 5)
    - Duke, Sarah P. (autochrome), circa 1910 (Box 5)
    - Biddle, Mary Duke (autochrome), circa 1910 (Box 5)
    - Biddle, Mary Duke (autochrome), circa 1910 (Box 5)
    - Photograph albums, circa 1938-1956, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Duke, Sarah Pearson Angier (carbon print? on paper sheet), circa 1925, 2 copies; 19 x 13 3/4 inches (Oversize-box 109)
      Two copies of a seated 3/4 profile portrait of Mary Duke Biddle's mother, Sarah Pearson Angier Duke, circa 1925, by a photographer or studio whose name appears as "Mishkeil, NY." The image is printed directly on the paper sheet, on which there is a decorative border and medallion with the name penciled in. The process appears to be a direct carbon print, a high-end photographic tecnique at the time.
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - Address books, 1950,undated (Box 7)
    - Printed, 1927 (Box 7)
    - School notes, 1903,undated (Box 7)
    - School publications: Biddle, Nicholas Benjamin Duke, 1938-1939,undated (Box 7)
    - Wedding, 1915 (Box 7)
    - Phonograph records: Piano performances of Mary Duke Biddle, undated (Box 7a)
- James H. Semans Family Papers, 1878-1953
  The James H. Semans Family Papers span the years 1878 to 1953, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1930s and 1940s. They consist of genealogical materials, correspondence, financial papers, legal papers, writings and speeches, scrapbooks, calendars, printed materials, student and professional reports, pictures, and miscellaneous materials relating to the Semans family of Uniontown, Pa. The papers particularly describe the life of James H. Semans, including the academic and professional course Dr. Semans took toward becoming a physician and the early years of his medical practice, before his marriage to Mary Duke Biddle Trent in 1953.
  The Correspondence Series especially illustrates Dr. Semans's relationships with his parents and several other family members and his medical training and career. Dr. Semans carried on considerable correspondence with his parents during the 1930s and 1940s, and with his sister Virginia and her husband Wendell A. Stone in the 1940s. The letters describe family life and Dr. Semans's academic, professional, and personal life. Many of these letters were written during Semans's medical residencies at Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore, St. Mary's Hospital in Pierre, S.D., Ancker Hospital in St. Paul, Minn., and various military base hospitals. He served on the urological service of Dr. Hugh H. Young at Johns Hopkins Hospital. There are also scattered letters from acquaintances.
  From 1938 to 1939 Dr. Semans served a medical internship in Pierre, S.D. In a series of letters to his parents he describes his work at the hospital and relationships with members of the staff, his impressions of the community and citizens including American Indians, and the surrounding countryside. Notable are Dr. Semans's descriptions of his St. Mary's Hospital mentor, Dr. Theodore E. Riggs, grandson of Stephen R. Riggs, a missionary to Indians. [Dr. Riggs is also mentioned in letters dated March 31 and April 15, 1944.]
  Beginning in 1946 the bulk of correspondence occurs between J.H. Semans and his medical colleagues. Much of it concerns the establishment of his Atlanta medical practice, arrangements for professional meetings and organizations, personnel references and other professional matters. There is some correspondence between Dr. Semans and his patients. The latter part of 1953 includes information on Dr. Semans's establishment of a medical practice in North Carolina and family and personal correspondence related to his marriage to Mary D.B. Trent.
  Most of the letters from the 1880s and early 1900s in the Correspondence Series are addressed to the father of James H. Semans, Thomas B. Semans, a successful businessman. They relate to family matters and business investments, including a coal enterprise in New Zealand. The Financial Papers Series and the Legal Papers Series include personal financial records created by Thomas B. Semans and records pertaining to his estate.
  The Writings and Speeches Series includes periodic diary entries made by Dr. Semans. Most diary entries date to 1946 wherein he describes various trips he made as he looked for a location to establish a medical practice. Most of the medical papers and speeches were prepared for medical professionals but some speeches were presented to local service clubs.
  The Scrapbook Series includes photographs, clippings, and correspondence from Dr. Hugh H. Young and others. Dr. Semans compiled and annotated an autobiographical scrapbook for the years 1910 to 1952. Types of materials similar to those in this scrapbook are located in the autobiographical files of the Speeches and Writings Series of the James H. and Mary D.B.T. Semans Family Papers.
  There are a variety of family photographs, chiefly of members of the Semans family, in the Pictures Series. There are some formal pictures of children's birthday parties (1910s, 1920s) and Uniontown houses, and some candid photographs made in Atlanta, Georgia, and Pierre, South Dakota. There are copy photographs of Semans family ancestors made from a cartes de visite album. See the James H. and Mary D.B.T. Semans Family Papers for pictures of the Semans family dated after 1953.
  - Genealogical Papers Series
    - Thomas B. Semans and descendants, 1892-1953,undated (Box 8)
  - Correspondence Series
    - 1878-1925 (Box 8)
    - 1934-1947, Dec., 12 folders (Box 8)
    - 1948-1953, 11 folders (Box 9)
  - Financial Papers Series
    - Thomas B. Semans, 1884-1921 (Box 10)
  - Legal Papers Series: Estate
    - Thomas B. Semans, 1941-1948, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Virginia B. Semans, undated (Box 10)
  - Writings and Speeches Series
    - Diary, 1946-1951 (Box 10)
    - Medical, 1941-1952,undated (Box 10)
    - Medical notes, 1940-1951,undated (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks Series
    - Annotation by J.H. Semans, 1910-1952 (Box 11)
    - Pages 1-20, 9 folders (Box 11)
  - Pictures Series
    - Uniontown, Pa., ca. 1911-1920 (Box 11)
    - Friends, undated (Box 11)
    - James H. Semans, ca. 1947-1953 (Box 11)
    - Francis M. Semans family, Uniontown, Pa. (Box 11)
    - Thomas B. Semans family, Uniontown, Pa., undated (Box 11)
    - Thomas B. and Virginia Belle (Smith) Semans, 1912, 1922, undated (Box 11)
    - Semans family, Uniontown, Pa., ca. 1860-1918, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Hilltop School (near Uniontown, Pa.), ca. 1916 (Box 11)
    - Pierre, S.D., 1930s (Box 11)
    - Thomas B. Semans family, undated (Box 93-A)
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - Calendars, 1947 (Box 11)
    - Calendars, 1947-1953, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Certificates and Awards, 1944, 1952 (Box 12)
    - Clippings, 1940s-1952 (Box 12)
    - Memberships, 1947-1955,undated (Box 12)
    - Printed, 1910 (Box 12)
    - School related, 1927, 1932,undated (Box 12)
- James H. and Mary D.B.T. Semans Family Papers, 1925-1991